<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Puget Sound Performance Trends</title>
    <description>Analysis and data for the Puget Sound region</description>
    <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Growth in Transit Ridership Outpacing Employment and Population Growth</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;growth-in-transit-ridership-outpacing-employment-and-population-growth&quot;&gt;Growth in Transit Ridership Outpacing Employment and Population Growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-july-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Transit boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monthly boardings on our regional transit system were up approximately 3.6% in the first five months of 2016, once again out-pacing employment and population growth. In all we had almost 2.7 million more boardings in the first five months of 2016 than we did in 2015 for a total of 76.9 million boardings through May 2016. If we look back over the past five years, transit ridership is up over 13% since May of 2011 with additional 8.9 million boardings in the first five months of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boardings on all modes of public transit (bus, light rail, street car and commuter rail) have increased so far in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;light-rail-ridership-continues-to-climb-after-opening-of-new-stations&quot;&gt;Light Rail Ridership continues to climb after opening of new stations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light rail boardings jumped significantly after the opening of the Capitol Hill and Husky Stadium Stations in March 2016 and ridership has continued to increase in the two full months following the March opening. Overall monthly boardings were up 798,000 on the region’s light rail and streetcar networks between May 2015 and May 2016, a 72% increase. Light rail boardings were up almost 5% between April and May of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Light Rail and Streetcar Boardings: January through May 2010 to 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-july-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Light Rail boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;strong-growth-in-ferry-ridership&quot;&gt;Strong Growth in Ferry Ridership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boardings on regional ferry routes have increased over 2015 levels for every month in 2016 so far for a total of 9.6 million boardings between January and May 2016, a 2.6% increase over 2015. This increase continues the trend of increasing ferry ridership that began in 2013 and represents a 9.5% ridership increase since 2010. Regional ferry ridership so far in 2016 is at its highest level since 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Ferry Boardings, January through May 2010 to 2016&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-july-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Ferry Boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ridership gains of the past three years follow nearly 10 years of flat or slowing declining ferry ridership as a result of various fare and route changes as well as shifting demographics in Kitsap County. Strong job growth as well as newer county provided passenger only service in the past 5 years is a likely reason for the recent growth in ferry ridership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-do-transit-and-ferry-boardings-matter&quot;&gt;Why do transit and ferry boardings matter?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transit and ferry boardings demonstrate how many people are traveling about the region in our transit system. The number of boardings can have impacts on the amount of traffic on our roads and the amount of ozone and carbon dioxide emitted into our air. A goal of our integrated land use and transportation plans is to increase the number of travel options available to people and to increase the amount of travel by modes other than the automobile. Transit and ferry boardings are one way to understand if more people are choosing these other travel options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monthly transit trends were delayed a couple of months due to technical issues with the National Transit Database – a key source of consistent data used in the reporting of transit service and usage in these trends. These issues have been resolved and the data is back to its normal monthly publication cycle. In August we will have data through the first half of the year and we will be comparing transit growth between 2015 and 2016 with the changes in population and employment that we have reported on so far this year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/07/08/transit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/07/08/transit/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Services sector continues to drive the region’s job growth</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;services-sector-continues-to-drive-the-regions-job-growth&quot;&gt;Services sector continues to drive the region’s job growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region has gained 17,300 jobs since January - with 3,700 new jobs added in April 2016. The job growth since April 2015 has averaged 3.2%. King and Snohomish Counties continue to be the major contributors to regional job growth. Growth in April was slightly higher than the 3,300 jobs that were added to the region in March 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region gained added almost 63,000 jobs between April 2015 and April 2016, about 6% more than the 59,000 jobs added between April 2014 and April 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/emp-apr-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Employment&quot; title=&quot;Seasonally Adjusted Annual Wage and Salary Employment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Annual Wage and Salary Employment (Seasonally Adjusted) Trend:  2011-2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;job-growth-varied-by-employment-sectors&quot;&gt;Job growth varied by employment sectors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region has continued to experience robust job growth in the services sector by adding 3,500 more jobs in April 2016. The services sector includes jobs from IT, business services, recreation and food services etc. The services sector gained about 35,000 jobs over the past year, 13,000 more than it did between April 2014 and April 2015. The construction sector grew at 5.1%, the fastest annual growth rate between April 2015 and April 2016 while the manufacturing sector experienced slight job declines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Annual Change in Wage and Salary Employment by Sector&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/emp-apr-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Employment&quot; title=&quot;Employment by Sector&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coming-up-in-july&quot;&gt;Coming up in July:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, PSRC kicked off the process to create a new Regional Economic Strategy for the Puget Sound Region. The new strategy will enhance understanding of the forces that drive the region’s economy, inform the region’s land use and transportation planning, and support state and local economic development initiatives. We will continue to examine job sector and other economic trends as the strategy is developed. For more information visit: http://www.psrc.org/econdev/res/.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/06/16/employment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/06/16/employment/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Transit Ridership Through February: Up Again</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;transit-ridership-through-february-up-again&quot;&gt;Transit Ridership Through February: Up Again&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-april-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Transit boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monthly boardings on our regional transit system were up a little more than 2% in the first two months of 2016. After a fairly flat January, ridership in February was up over 5% compared to 2015.   It should be noted that we did benefit from an extra day this February – but the estimated ridership from one extra day does not account for the overall increase of 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All modes of public transit (bus, light rail, street car and commuter rail) were up in February 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-do-we-compare-nationally&quot;&gt;How do we compare nationally?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. National Comparison of Transit Ridership&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-april-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Transit Comparision&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transit Boardings in the Central Puget Sound Region have grown faster than any other Large Metropolitan Area in the United States since 2005.  In all, transit boardings have been growing at 3.6% per year since 2005 in our region. The next fastest growing area is Tampa-St Petersburg at around 3.1%. Our annual transit growth is 3 times faster than the Portland Metro region and our 185 million boardings in 2015 were the 8th highest out of the following 20 metropolitan areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vanpool-capital-of-the-country&quot;&gt;Vanpool capital of the country&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. Vanpool Usage&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-april-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Vanpool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Puget Sound Region continues to have the largest vanpool usage in the country – exceeding the next closest region of Los Angeles County by over 1 million vanpool trips a year. When you consider the relative population of the region – Los Angeles County is over 10 million people and we are about 3.9 million, our vanpool boardings per capita are almost three times higher than Los Angeles and the highest of any region in the country. The trend has continued into 2016 and vanpool usage in the first two months of 2016 is up slightly over 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coming-up-in-may&quot;&gt;Coming up in May&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, we will see what ridership looked like in March - the first month of data with light rail serving Capitol Hill and the University of Washington. Although the majority of the month’s data will be prior to the light rail expansion, it should provide an initial glimpse at the change. It will also give us a glimpse at the totals for the first quarter of ridership in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/04/25/transit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/04/25/transit/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Strong Passenger Growth for SeaTac Airport Continues into 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;strong-passenger-growth-for-seatac-airport-continues-into-2016&quot;&gt;Strong Passenger Growth for SeaTac Airport Continues into 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/airport-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Airport&quot; title=&quot;Airport Passengers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Passengers at SeaTac Airport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many signs of a strong economy and vibrant quality of life in a region – and one of them is the amount of people who chose to travel to and from a region. It is estimated the over 75% of airline travel is for leisure but business related travel brings in a larger share of revenue to airlines – and this travel grows when the economy is growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-the-trend-for-airline-passenger-volumes-at-seattle-tacoma-international-airport&quot;&gt;What is the trend for airline passenger volumes at Seattle-Tacoma International Airport?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seattle-Tacoma International Airport (SeaTac) was the 13th busiest airport in the United States last year and surpassed 42 million passengers for the first time in its history. In all, there were almost 5 million more passengers passing through the airport in 2015, a 13% increase over 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2016, an additional 364,000 passengers flew in and out of SeaTac airport, a 13.6% increase over February 2015, for a total monthly passenger volume of over 3.0 million. This marks the first time the airport has moved over 3 million people in the month of February and is 669,000 more passengers than February 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-the-busiest-month-for-travel&quot;&gt;What is the busiest month for travel?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that the week of Thanksgiving is the busiest week of the year at an airport but many people might be surprised to know that the summer months, especially July and August, are typically the busiest months for travel in the year. This reflects the summer travel that occurs throughout the month – unlike November which is pretty light for the first half of the month – as well as the fact that there are 31 days in each of those summer months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-air-cargo&quot;&gt;What about Air Cargo?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/airport-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Airport&quot; title=&quot;Air Cargo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Annual Air Cargo at SeaTac Airport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 330 metric tons of air cargo Air Cargo was moved through SeaTac airport in 2015 – up slightly from 2014 and ranking 19th in the country. Approximately 18% all air cargo moved is mail. February 2016 air cargo levels have reduced below 2015 levels and are slightly higher than the total amount of air cargo moved through the airport in February 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;which-airline-moves-the-most-passengers&quot;&gt;Which Airline moves the most passengers?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/airport-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Airport&quot; title=&quot;Airlines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. Passengers by Airline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alaska Airlines, which includes Horizon Air, carried over 55% of the passenger volume in February 2016. Delta Airlines is the next largest airline by passenger volume at approximately 18% of total passenger volume in February 2016. Delta Airlines has increased their market share 7% over the past two years and is currently the fastest growing carrier at Sea-Tac Airport – averaging 39% passenger volume growth per year on the last 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passenger volume trends are updated monthly and will be considered along with other economic indicators to understand the story of growth in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/25/airport/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/25/airport/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slow Start to 2016 on our Region&#39;s Freeways</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;slow-start-to-2016-on-our-regions-freeways&quot;&gt;Slow Start to 2016 on our Region’s Freeways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/delay-mar-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;VHDelay&quot; title=&quot;Vehicle Hours of Delay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Vehicle Hours of Delay on the Freeway System&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic congestion on our freeways increased in the first two months of 2016, but the rate of increase has moderated compared to last year. In all, commuters on our region’s freeways spent almost 1.7 million hours sitting in congestion over the first two months of 2016 – up 17% from the first two months of 2015. When you consider the cost of this delay in terms of lost time, extra fuel and general wear and tear on your vehicle, this delay totaled over $49 milliion dollars for the first two months of the year. This equates to a daily cost of delay of approximately $1.2 million dollars per weekday on freeways in our region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-do-things-compare-by-corridor&quot;&gt;How do things compare by corridor?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Vehicle Hours of Delay by Corridor&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/delay-mar-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;VHDelay&quot; title=&quot;Delay by Corridor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, delay across freeway corridors has increased between 2015 and 2016 but there are noticeable differences by freeway. I-5 and I-405 account for approximately 90% of the regional delay on freeways. Of this, I-5 accounted for over 64% of the regional freeway delay in the first two months of 2016, up from approximately 61% in 2015. Delay on I-405 between Tukwila and Lynnwood dropped between 2015 and 2016 and now accounts for approximately 24% of the freeway delay (down from 30% in 2015). SR 520 was the other corridor in which delay in 2016 did not increase over 2015 levels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/16/delay/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/16/delay/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rail Ridership Continues to Climb</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;rail-ridership-continues-to-climb&quot;&gt;Rail Ridership Continues to Climb&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-march-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Transit boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monthly boardings on Link Light Rail between SeaTac Airport and Downtown Seattle and Tacoma Link service between Tacoma Dome Station and Downtown Tacoma topped 1 million boardings in January 2016 – almost twice what the boardings were in January 2010. In all, January 2016 light rail boardings were 3.7% higher than January 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound Transit’s Sounder Commuter Rail boardings also increased almost 4% between 2015 and 2016, increasing to over 325,000 monthly boardings in January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-buses&quot;&gt;What about buses?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/transit-march-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transit Boardings&quot; title=&quot;Bus boardings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January boardings on our region’s buses were down about 1% in January 2016 compared with January 2015, but still more than 7% higher than they were in January 2010. Boardings were down on all our operators except one, Community Transit, who experienced growth of approximately 1.5% between January 2015 and January 2016. King County Metro boardings were down around 0.5% and the largest drops were on Pierce and Kitsap Transit. Kitsap Transit was the only operator who had a reduction in service hours in January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several things to keep in mind when looking at monthly data – and for transit a big one is how many work days there are in the month. January 2016 had 21 weekdays in it, January 2015 had 22. One day doesn’t sound like much, but it resulted in 4.5% fewer workdays being observed in the monthly data in 2016.  All things considered, bus boardings were flat in January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-was-community-transit-up&quot;&gt;Why was Community Transit up?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past several years of transit data have shown strong demand even when service hours have been down. One big difference for Community Transit this past January were service hours – up almost 10% in 2016. This increase reflects the re-addition of Sunday service to Community Transit that occurred in June 2015. This was the first of the additions for Community Transit – the first service increase related to the successful passage of the November 2015 ballot measure will go on-line in March 27th with even more service planned to come online in September 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coming-up-in-april&quot;&gt;Coming up in April&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April we will see what ridership looked like in February - the last month of data before the University Link opening. It will also include one extra day of ridership with our Leap Year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/15/transit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/03/15/transit/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Miles Traveled By Car Starting to Rise</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;miles-traveled-by-car-starting-to-rise&quot;&gt;Miles Traveled By Car Starting to Rise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;post-image&quot;&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-1.png&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Vehicle Miles Traveled” is a measure that demonstrates how much people are traveling about the region. The amount of vehicle miles traveled has impacts on the amount of traffic on our roads and the amount of ozone and carbon dioxide emitted into the air. A goal of our integrated land use and transportation planning is to increase the number of travel options available to people and to lower the amount of vehicle miles traveled by automobile. Reducing the amount of miles driven per capita is an integral part of the State’s Climate Change Policy and a key part of the Region’s Four-Part Greenhouse Gas Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-overall-vehicle-miles-traveled-trends-in-our-region&quot;&gt;What are Overall Vehicle Miles Traveled trends in our Region?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The total annual vehicle miles traveled in the PSRC Region has remained fairly flat regionally since 2010, even though the region has been experiencing strong population and job growth since 2010. The daily miles driven per person was approximately 21.4 miles per person per day in 2014, levels last seen in the late 1980’s and below the peak of 24 miles per person per day in the late 1990’s. Regional data will not be available until the summer of 2016 but initial trends around the state show a possible increase in VMT occurred in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;post-image&quot;&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled Per Person&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-2.png&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled Per Person&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-the-state-as-a-whole&quot;&gt;What about the state as a whole?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although VMT per Capita still remained below 2010 levels in 2015, there has been a fairly strong growth in miles traveled around the state in the past year. This growth in VMT can likely be attributed to our strong economy and population growth but also the cost of fuel. As shown in the figure below, VMT changes since 2010 around the state has mirrored the average cost of gas – with VMT generally increasing as the cost of fuel has decreased. The sharp drop in fuel prices in 2015 is likely a large indicator of the strong growth in VMT in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;post-image&quot;&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-3.png&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/vmt-feb-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 3. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled Statewide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


  &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3. Daily Vehicle Miles Traveled Statewide&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-future-implications&quot;&gt;What are Future Implications?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low fuel prices and continued population and job growth looks to be increasing overall VMT over the past few years. VMT per capita remains below the highs of the late 1990’s but it will be important to return to  reductions in the amount of vehicle miles traveled per person to maintain our air quality and traffic congestions goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/29/driving/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/29/driving/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>After Years of Decline, Ferry Ridership is On the Rise</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-years-of-decline-ferry-ridership-is-on-the-rise&quot;&gt;After Years of Decline, Ferry Ridership is On the Rise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/ferry-ridership.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ferries&quot; title=&quot;Ferries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Regional Annual Boardings by Ferry Operator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferry Boardings are a measure that demonstrates how many people are traveling about the region on our region’s ferry system. The ferry system is an important access link to jobs, health care and recreation for citizens on both sides of Puget Sound. The Ferry system is also the only means of access to Vashon Island. There are currently four providers of ferry service in the region with county level service provided for passenger only service and the Washington State Ferries that serve both cars and walk on passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-the-overall-ferry-trend-in-our-region&quot;&gt;What is the Overall Ferry trend in our Region?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annual ridership on the Washington State Ferries (WSF) in the Puget Sound region increased in 2015 by almost 3%. This follows a 2.4% increase in 2014 and was the third straight annual increase after a long stretch of declining ridership dating back to 1999.  WSF ferry ridership in 2015 was 21.2 million distributed over six auto-routes, and each route had increasing ridership. The peak for regional ferry ridership was 24 million riders in 1999. Frequent fare increases, gas price hikes and the recent recession have contributed to a 12% ridership drop since that peak, recent gains notwithstanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferry ridership on the county provided service has experienced strong growth since 2006, growing almost 70%. County level operators have increased service frequency over this time period to meet the growing demand. A large part of this growth is on King County Ferry District service to Vashon Island and West Seattle. Overall annual boardings neared 1.2m on county provided service in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-did-ridership-vary-throughout-the-year-in-2015&quot;&gt;How did ridership vary throughout the year in 2015?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ridership on the ferry system mixes commuters and recreational travelers. Ridership varies by month and by route but in general the highest ridership months for the ferry system are June through August. In these months the biggest increases in ridership occur on the routes that connect to the Kitsap Peninsula in Bremerton, Bainbridge Island and Kingston as well as Whidbey Island. Routes on and off of Vashon Island and the West Seattle Water Taxi tend to have more stable ridership patterns throughout the course of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/ferry-monthly.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ferries&quot; title=&quot;Ferries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Regional Annual Boardings by Month&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-did-mode-of-access-differ-by-route-in-2015&quot;&gt;How did mode of access differ by route in 2015?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walk on passenger volumes vary greatly by route. The two largest walk-on volume routes serve Colman Dock in Downtown Seattle from Bremerton and Bainbridge Island. Bainbridge Island carried over 3 million walk-on passengers in 2015, approximately 49% of its total ridership. The Bremerton route carried over 1.6 million walk on passengers, 63% of its total ridership. Walk on trips made up roughly 10%-15% of the total annual ridership for the remaining WSF routes. Approximately 32% of all ferry passengers in the Puget Sound Region were walk on passengers in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/ferry-routes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ferries&quot; title=&quot;Ferries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. Regional Annual Boardings by Mode of Access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferry service between Mukilteo and Clinton (Whidbey Island) carried more vehicles in 2015 than any other route followed closely by the Kingston-Edmonds route. In all, 89% of the total passengers on the Mukilteo-Clinton route access the ferry by automobile, the highest share of vehicle access in the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-the-future-implications&quot;&gt;What are the Future Implications?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferry routes will continue to connect the communities across the Puget Sound and are a critical link between people and the services they need. The more recent growth in both the supply and demand for passenger only ferry service will be important to understand as the region continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/26/ferries/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/26/ferries/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wet and Slow January</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;wet-and-slow-january&quot;&gt;Wet and Slow January&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/delay1.png&quot; alt=&quot;VHDelay&quot; title=&quot;Vehicle Hours of Delay&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Annual Vehicle Hours of Delay on the Freeway System&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did your trip to work in January seem even slower than usual? If so, you were not alone. Delay on our freeways increased 32% between January 2015 and January 2016. The increases were seen on all our freeways with the greatest change occurring on I-5 while congestion on I-405 increased the least (13%). In all, we spent an additional 211,000 hours in traffic over the 21 weekdays in January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-happened-in-2016&quot;&gt;What happened in 2016?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many things that factor into traffic congestion, but the biggest three in January 2016 were likely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction closures on Hwy 99.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;53K jobs added over the past year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rain, rain and more rain!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/delay2.png&quot; alt=&quot;VHDelay&quot; title=&quot;Rain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although each of these items likely led to our delay increase, it is very likely that Mother Nature had a big role in our congestion last month. It is estimated that approximately ½ of all congestion on our roadways is not related to how many people are trying to use them but is instead related to things that don’t happen every day – like collisions and vehicle breakdowns. Wet roadways can play a big part in the number of collisions that occur and thus can have a big impact on traffic congestion. In January 2016, over 70% of our weekdays had rain and over half of those had more than ¼” of rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-i-405&quot;&gt;What about I-405?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/delay3.png&quot; alt=&quot;VHDelay&quot; title=&quot;I-405&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I-405 was unique compared to the other freeway corridors in January 2016 in that it had sections of the corridor that experienced increases in delay and others that had decreases in delay in 2016. Between Bellevue and Tukwila, the overall congestion on I-405 increased at a similar rate as many of the other freeways in the region. Between Bothell and Bellevue, the overall delay for all the freeway lanes decreased almost 60% compared to 2015 – the only large freeway corridor to see a reduction in delay in the region. North of Bothell, delays more than doubled between 2015 and 2016 – the largest percent increase for a corridor section in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/19/delay/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/19/delay/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Region adds 54,300 Jobs in 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;region-adds-54300-jobs-in-2015&quot;&gt;Region adds 54,300 Jobs in 2015&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the Puget Sound region gained 54,300 jobs, marking the fifth consecutive year of job growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region added more than 241,300 jobs between 2010 and 2015, compared to loss of 6,600 jobs in the previous five-year period from 2005 to 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Annual Wage and Salary Employment (Seasonally Adjusted) Trend:  2010-2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/emp-feb-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Employment&quot; title=&quot;Annual Wage and Salary Employment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;growth-of-jobs-by-5-year-increments&quot;&gt;Growth of Jobs by 5-year increments&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/trends/images/2016/emp-feb-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Employment&quot; title=&quot;Growth of Jobs by 5-Year Increments&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;region-starts-off-2016-by-adding-150-jobs-per-day&quot;&gt;Region starts off 2016 by adding 150 jobs per day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region added 150 jobs per day, totaling 4,500 jobs in the first month of 2016. The majority of the job gains occurred in King and Snohomish Counties. The annual job growth rate remained around 3% in January 2016 despite a time when the retail sector traditionally ends seasonal holiday work. In December 2015, the region gained 5,200 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region has continued to experience robust job growth in the past six years. The region has added 269,600 jobs since January 2010. The region gained 58,000 jobs since January 2015, which is 6% higher than 54,600 jobs added between January 2014 and January 2015. The regional civilian labor force increased 1.6% since January 2015 and the unemployment rate in January 2016 remained at 5.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coming-up-in-april&quot;&gt;Coming up in April:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll look at the regional job data for the month of February 2016 and investigate how the job trends further into 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/17/employment/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://psrc.github.io/trends/updates///2016/02/17/employment/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>